A Guide to the Papers of Robert E. Lee, 1830-1870
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Robert E. Lee 1830-1870
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
: Various
This collection consists of ca. 130 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was acquired through gift and purchase, ca. 1835-present.
Biographical/Historical Information
American soldier, general in the Confederate States army, was the youngest son of major-general Henry Lee ("Light Horse Harry") and Ann Hill Carter Lee. Robert Edward Lee was born at Stratford, Westmoreland County, Virginia, January 19, 1807, and entered West Point in 1825. Graduating four years later second in his class, he was given a commission in the U.S. Engineer Corps. In 1831 he married Mary Ann Randolph Custis, daughter of George Washington Parke Custis, the adopted son of George Washington and the grandson of Martha Washington. The Lees had seven children. All three of their sons served in the Confederate army. George Washington Custis and William Henry Fitzhugh ("Rooney") attained the rank of Major General and Robert E. Lee, Jr., that of Captain. The latter served as a private in the Rockbridge Artillery at the Battle of Antietam.
In 1836 Lee became first lieutenant, and in 1838 captain. In this rank he took part in the Mexican War, repeatedly winning distinction for conduct and bravery. After the war he was employed in engineer work at Washington and Baltimore, during which time, as before the war, he resided on the Arlington estate, near Washington, which had come to him through his wife.
In 1852 he was appointed superintendent of West Point, and during his three years there he carried out many changes in the academy. Under him as cadets were his son George Washington Custis Lee, his nephew, Fitzhugh Lee and J. E. B. Stuart, all of whom became general officers in the Civil War. In 1855 he was appointed as lieutenant-colonel to the 2nd Cavalry, commanded by Colonel Sidney Johnston, with whom he served on the Texas border.
In 1859, while at Arlington on leave, he was summoned to command the United States troops sent to deal with the John Brown raid on Harper's Ferry. In March 1861 he was made colonel of the 1st U.S. Cavalry. Lee's career in the U.S. army ended with the secession of Virginia in the following month. The Federal authorities offered Lee the command of the field army about to invade the South, which he refused. Resigning his commission, he made his way to Richmond and was at once made a major-general in the Virginia forces. A few weeks later he became a brigadier-general (then the highest rank) in the Confederate service. He assumed command of the Army of Northern Virginia in May 1862 and led the Confederate Army in Virginia for the next three years.
Lee surrendered the Army of Northern Virginia at Appomattox Court House, on April 9, 1865. For a few months Lee lived quietly in Richmond, making his formal submission to the Federal authorities and urging Southern acceptance of the new conditions. In August he was offered, and accepted, the presidency of Washington College (now Washington and Lee University), a post which he occupied until his death on October 12, 1870. He was buried in the college grounds.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of ca. 130 items, chiefly letters of Robert E. Lee to friends, family and staff.
Contents List
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1830 May 8, ALS 3 p. on 2 l. (Box 1)
  #1085
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1830 September 22, ALS 3 p. on 2 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1830 September 30, ALS 3 p. on 2 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1830 October 12, ALS 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1830 November 16, ALS 3 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1831 January 4, ALS 3 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1831 February 27, ALS 3 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1831 May 26, ALS 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1831 June 15, ALS 3 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1831 October 12, ALS 3 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1832 April 6, ALS 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1832 August 17, ALS 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1832 September 1, ALS 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1832 September 28, ALS 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1833 February 1, ALS 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1833 April 6, ALS 3 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1833 September 16, ALS 3 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to L[ittleton] W[aller] Tazewell 1833 September 17, ALS 1 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  #10009
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1833 December 6, ALS 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1834 June 30, ALS 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1834 August 20, ALS 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Mr. Blair 1835 January 13, ANS 1 p. on 1 printed leaf. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1835 February 24, ALS 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1835 May 17, ALS 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1835 May 29, ALS 3 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1835 May 31, ALS 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1836 May 2, ALS 3 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  #990-b
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1836 August 2, ALS 3 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1837 January 26, ALS 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Brigadier General R. Jones 1837 April 10, ALS 1 p., letter in another hand but signed by Lt. Lee of the Engineer Corps. (Box 1)
  #4703
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1837 August 15, ALS 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Mary Ann Custis Lee 1837 August 21, ALS 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee and M.C. Lee to George Washington Parke Custis 1837 August 25, ALS 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1837 October 8, ALS 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1838 May 18, ALS 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1838 December 24, ALS 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Account of Robert E. Lee with the U.S. government re the Improvement of the Mississippi River, Above the Mouth of the Ohio River (bottom of account is cut off) 1838, ADS 1 l. (Box 1)
  ##441
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1839 January 7, ALS 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  ##1085
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1840 January 30, ALS 3 p. on 2 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1840 February 23, ALS 3 p. on 2 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1840 August 22, ALS 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Mary Ann Custis Lee 1841 April 18, ALS 3 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Receipt for a mare & her colt, signed by Robert E. Lee, to R.W. Carter 1843 February 10, ADS 1 p. (Box 1)
  #1959
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1843 February 14, ALS (Box 1)
  4 p. on 1 l.; top of the letter is trimmed away.
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1843 July 24, ALS 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1843 August 17, ALS 4 p. on 1 l.; part of letter trimmed away. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1844 September 1, ALS 3 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1846 July 13, ALS 3 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1846 September 1, ALS 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Joseph E. Johnston 1846-1865, 6 items. Photocopies only. (Box 1)
  1846 will of Robert E. Lee showing that he owned a slave named "Nancy" and her three children, together with a letter from Judith S. Hynson of the Jessie Ball DuPont Memorial Library at Stratford, Va., quoting an 1856 letter from Lee to his wife on the subject of slavery. There are also copies of letters from Lee to his sister, April, 20, 1861 to Winfield Scott, April 20, 1861 to Jefferson Davis, July 8, 1863 and a copy in an unidentified hand, signed by Lee, of General Order No. 9, April 10, 1865. #12132
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1848 February 13, ALS 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1848 March 18, ALS 4 p. on 1 l.with envelope. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1848 May 15, ALS 4 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Mapa de la Sierra Gorda [1848] (Box 1)
  Copied for Lee; with his notes and signature. #5096-a
- Robert E. Lee to Henry A. DuBois 1853 February 9, ALS 1 p. on 1 l., typescript and photostatic copy only. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Capt. J. Monroe 1853 May 3, Photocopy only. (Box 1)
  #38-257
- Robert E. Lee to William Henry Fitzhugh Lee 1853 June 15, ALS 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1855 May 10, ALS 4 p. on 1 l., with envelope (Box 1)
- R.E. Lee to William [Overton Winston?] 1856 July 24, ALS 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  #8482
- Orders to Captain Stoneman, 2nd Cavalry, San Antonio, signed by Robert E. Lee 1857 August 31, ADS 1 p. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Edward C. Turner 1858 February 13, ALS 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Major Earl Van Dorn 1860 June 27, ALS 3 p. on 2 l. (Box 1)
- Hugh Sheffey to Robert E. Lee, with endorsements by John B. Baldwin, Capt. John D. Imboden, Sam M. Garlan, Roger A. Pryor and accompanied by a note from Lee, who refers the request to Colonel Thomas J. Jackson 1861 April 27, ANS 3 p. on 2 l. (Box 1)
  #4406
- Robert E. Lee to Cary Charles Cocke 1861 June 10, Photocopy only. (Box 1)
  #5313-f
- Robert E. Lee to Colonel J.W. Ware 1861 June 19, LS 1 p. (Box 1)
  #6136
- Robert E. Lee to Colonel J.W. Ware 1861 June 28, LS 1 p. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Joseph E. Johnston 1861 July 24, ALS 1 p. (Box 1)
  #11576
- Alfred Beckley to Robert E. Lee 1861 August 21, 25, Photocopy. (Box 1)
  #6846-bb
- Robert E. Lee to Edward C. Turner 1861 September 14, ALS 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  #7959
- Robert E. Lee to Philip St. George Cocke 1861-1865, 10 items. Photocopies only. (Box 1)
  #2433-f
- Robert E. Lee, telegram to Major Harman 1862 April 18, Photocopy only. (Box 1)
  #3327
- Thomas J. Jackson to Robert E. Lee 1862 June 11, Photocopy only. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Major General John Bankhead Magruder 1862 June 26, ALS 1 p. (Box 1)
  #2562
- Thomas L. Rosser to Robert E. Lee 1862 July 25, ALS, 5 p. on 5 l. (Box 1)
  #1171-j
- Robert E. Lee to Colonel J. Thompson Brown 1862 August 7, ALS 1 p. (Box 1)
  #10100-c
- Robert E. Lee to Anne B. Carter Wickham 1862 November 11, D, 1 p. 19th century copy. (Box 1)
  Lee expresses his regret that Williams Carter Wickham, her son, has again been wounded but explains that he cannot be spared from returning to duty in the army
  #15753
- Robert E. Lee to [J.E.B.] Stuart [1862], ALS 1 p. (Box 1)
  #49
- J.E.B. Stuart to Robert E. Lee 1862 October 12, ALS 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  #448
- Robert E. Lee to Major Duffy 1862 [November] 18, Photocopy only. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Albert Taylor Bledsoe 1863 February 18, ANS, on verso of ALS, 1863 February 16, Bledsoe to Lee, 1 p. (Box 1)
  #2769-a
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1863 March 24, ALS 2 p. (Box 1)
  #11424
- Robert E. Lee to Charles Carter Lee 1863 May 24, ALS 5 p. on 2 l. (20th century copy) (Box 1)
  #438
- William F. Wickham to Robert E. Lee 1863 June 28, AD; 2 drafts. (Box 1)
  Wickham writes about the arrival at Hickory Hill of Union cavalry, who carried off General William Henry Fitzhugh Lee as a prisoner in Wickham’s carriage, as well as horses and slaves, and reports that Charlotte Lee’s health is not good and that she is much distressed at her husband’s capture.
- J.E.B. Stuart to [Robert E. Lee] 1863 September 19, ALS 3 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  #5660
- Robert E. Lee to Edward Willis 1864 March 11, Photocopy only. (Box 1)
  #7837
- Robert E. Lee to Mrs. J.S. Heiskell 1864 March 24, ALS 2 p. on 1 l., with typescript. (Box 1)
  #38-186
- Robert E. Lee to George Wasington Custis Lee 1864 March 29, Photocopy only. (Box 1)
  #9320
- Robert E. Lee circular letter to Commanding officers 1864 June 3, ALS 1 p. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to General Thomas L. Rosser 1864 July 28, LS 1 p. (Box 1)
  #1171
- Jubal A. Early to Robert E. Lee [1864] August 10, Photocopy only. (Box 1)
  #4166
- Robert E. Lee to Mrs. Paschal Jennings Fowlkes 1864 September 17, Photocopy only. (Box 1)
  #5355
- Robert E. Lee to Colonel Cabell 1864 December 19, ALS 1 p., mounted on board. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Ulysses S. Grant 1865 April 9, Photocopy only. (Box 1)
  #10645
- Robert E. Lee, General Order No. 9 1865 April 9, D, 1 p. (Box 1)
  19th century? copy in unidentified hand. #793
- Robert E. Lee, General Order No. 9 1865 April 10, DS. 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 1)
  #5711
- Robert E. Lee, General Order No. 9 1865 April 10, Photocopy only. (Box 1)
  #5155
- Robert E. Lee, General Order No. 9 1865 April 10, Photographic copy only. (Box 1)
  Draft? #5155
- Robert E. Lee, General Order No. 9 1865 April 10, Photocopy only. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee to Phillip Slaughter 1865 August 31, Photocopy only. (Box 1)
  #6020
- Robert E. Lee to Williams Carter Wickham 1865 October 3, ALS (Box 1)
  Lee writes about Henry T. Wickham’s attendance at Washington College in Lexington and Lee’s plan to write a history about military campaigns in Virginia during the Civil War
- Williams Carter Wickham to Robert E. Lee 1865 October 13, D. (Box 1)
  Draft in the hand of Lucy Wickham of Williams Carter Wickham's reply to 1865 October 3 letter of Robert E. Lee, above.
- Robert E. Lee to the Rev. Francis Sprigg 1865 October 21, ALS 1 p. (Box 1)
- Robert E. Lee, testimonial on behalf of Chaning M. Smith 1865 November 6, Photocopy only. (Box 1)
  #5749
- Robert E. Lee to Hunter McGuire 1866 September 15, Photocopy only. (Box 2)
  #9302
- Robert E. Lee to Colonel Charles S. Venable 1866 March 8, ALS 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 2)
- Robert E. Lee to Professor Charles S. Venable 1866 July 6, ALS 3 p. on 1 l., with envelope. (Box 2)
  #5655-a
- Robert E. Lee to Dr. A[lbert] T[aylor] Bledsoe 1866 October 8, ALS 1 p. (Box 2)
  #3461
- Robert E. Lee to General Thomas L. Rosser 1866 December 13, ALS 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 2)
- John D. Carter to Faculty of Washington College 1867 January 17, 3 p. on 1 l., with pencilled notes by Robert E. Lee, repaired. (Box 2)
  #5241
- Robert E. Lee to John B. Minor 1867 January 17, ALS 4 p. on 2 l. (Box 2)
  #38-602, interfiled with 3750
- Robert E. Lee to Mrs. S.A. Rees 1867 February 6, ALS 2 p. on 1 l., repaired. (Box 2)
- Robert E. Lee to Colonel E. Fontaine 1867 July 9, ALS 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 2)
  #6269-g
- Robert E. Lee to Colonel E. Fontaine 1867 July 9, ALS 1 p. (Box 2)
- Robert E. Lee to Socrates Maupin 1868 June 23, ALS 1 p., with envelope. (Box 2)
  #2478-a
- Robert E. Lee to W.A. Morgan 1868 December 3, ALS 1 p. (Box 2)
  #1275
- Robert E. Lee to Major Jed Hotchkiss 1868 December 14, ALS 1 p. (Box 2)
  #2822
- Robert E. Lee to Major Jed Hotchkiss 1868 December 16, ALS 1 p. (Box 2)
- Robert E. Lee to Henry Tutwiler 1869 April 8, Photocopy only. (Box 2)
  #10156
- Robert E. Lee to Edmund Pendleton 1869 April, Photocopy only. (Box 2)
  #5779
- Robert E. Lee to Basil L. Gildersleeve 1869 July 9, ALS 1 p., with envelope. (Box 2)
  #RG-21/90.902
- Robert E. Lee to Major Jed Hotchkiss 1869 October 20, ALS 1 p. (Box 2)
- Robert E. Lee to the students of Washington College 1869 [November] 23, Photocopy only. (Box 2)
  #9141
- Robert E. Lee to Major Jed Hotchkiss 1869 December 24, ALS 2 p. on 1 l. (Box 2)
- Robert E. Lee to W. Gordon McCabe 1870 February 9, ALS 1 p. (Box 2)
  #10568
- Robert E. Lee to T[homas] Hewitt Key 1870 February 17, ALS 2 p. on 1 l., with envelope. (Box 2)
  #10300
- Robert E. Lee to Joseph Henry 1870 March 11, Photocopy. (Box 2)
  Original in the Huntington Library.
  #2776
- Robert E. Lee to Annie Wickham [Anne Carter Wickham Renshaw Byerly] 1870 May 23, AL; signature excised. (Box 2)
  Lee promises to stop by “Hickory Hill” to visit if at all possible on his way back to Lexington.
- Robert E. Lee, "I will place the appt. under the President's..." n.d., ADS 1 p. (Box 2)
  #2723
- Robert E. Lee autograph n.d. (Box 2)
  #2926
- Hair from Traveller's mane; with confirmation note n.d., 1 p. (Box 2)
  #9513-c